Finding Aid for the Frances M. Crater Papers
Special Collections Manuscripts and Rare Books
- Subject Files - Other
  - Women’s Studies - Scarritt College, 1973 - 1974 (Box 9, Folder 9)
- Subject files – People
  - Baker, Howard H., Jr. - Senator (R) from Tennessee - correspondence (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - Brock, William E., III - Senator (R) from Tennessee - correspondence and other papers (See also Box 7, folder 6 - Equal Credit Opportunity Act) (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - Card, Emily - Congress Committee (Box 9, Folder 12)
  - Crater, Flora - Statement on the War to North Virginia NOW, April 7, 1971; interview with Fran Crater, NOW member, Nashville, TN (Box 9, Folder 13)
  - Duncan, John J. (R) Representative 2nd District - Ralph Nader Congress Project Citizens Look at Congress (Box 9, Folder 14)
  - Evins, Joe L., (D) Representative 4th District - Ralph Nader Congress Project Citizens Look at Congress (Box 9, Folder 15)
  - Fulton, Richard H. (D) Representative 5th District, Congress of the United States (Box 9, Folder 16)
  - Heide, Wilma Scott - President of NOW - “A Feminist Perspective on Manipulation of Woman (woman includes man)”, November 8, 1973 at a symposium at the University of Wisconsin and other materials (Box 9, Folder 17)
  - Henry, Douglas (D) State Senator, Tennessee - correspondence (Box 9, Folder 18)
  - Hoffmann, Martin R., General Counsel - Statement before the Subcommittee #2, U. S. Dept. of Defense, House Armed Services Committee, June 5, 1974 (Box 9, Folder 19)
  - Horrobin, Dr. Jean Margaret - Testimony - “ Genetic Counseling and the Pre-Natal Diagnosis of Genetic Disorders” before the Senate Judiciary Sub-Committee on Constitutional Amendments, June 4, 1974 (Box 9, Folder 20)
  - Lambert, Kendall - Questionnaire - Profile of a Liberated Woman (Box 9, Folder 21)
  - Middendorf, J. William II - Secretary of the Navy - Statement before subcommittee #2 concerning Legislation on Women at the Service Academies, June 12, 1974 (Box 9, Folder 22)
  - Shanker, Albert - President of the American Federation of Teachers, AFL – CIO - Statement for the Special Sub-committee on Education: Hiring Policies in Higher Education, September 25, 1974 (Box 9, Folder 23)
  - Shields, Katheryn - State Legislative Co-ordinator - Independence, Missouri (Box 9, Folder 24)
- Publications
  - Children’s Nonsexist Coloring Book, copyright 1972 by Rainbow Institute (Box 9, Folder 25)
  - Citizens’ Advisory Council on the Status of Women - Women in, 1970 (Box 9, Folder 26)
  - Citizen’s Advisory Council on the Status of Women (Box 9, Folder 27)
  - The Equal Rights Amendment and Alimony and Child Support Laws, Jan. 1972 (Box 9, Folder 27)
  - Interpretation of the Equal Rights Amendment in Accordance with Legislative History (Box 9, Folder 27)
  - Recognition of Economic Contribution of Homemakers and Protection of Children in Divorce Law and Practice (Box 9)
  - The Equal Rights Amendment: Hearings before the Subcommittee on Constitutional Amendments of the Committee on the Judiciary United States Senate, 91st. Congress..., May 5, 6, 7, 1970 (Box 9, Folder 28)
- Publications
  - Free to Be You and Me (conceived by Marlo Thomas), 1974 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - NOW - Sex Discrimination in Employment: What to Know About It, What to Do About it - Eastern Massachusetts Chapter, Equal Economic Opportunity Task Force, 2nd edition, March 1973 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - NOW - Voter’s Information Handbook, 1974 Conference (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - The Plastic Broom (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - The Politics of Housework” by Pat Mainardi (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Redstockings - Feminist Revolution, 1975 (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Services in Affirmative Action and Equal Opportunity (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - State of Tennessee - Health Facilities Commission Interim Guidelines (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - Tennessee Commission for Human Development Annual Report, 1967 - 8, 1971 (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - U.S. Civil Service Commission - Employment, 1970, 1972, 1973 (Box 10, Folder 10)
  - U.S. Civil Service Commission-“The Federal Woman’s Program a Point of View; Personal Qualifications Statement (Standard Form 171); Current Federal Examination Announcements, Jan.- Feb. 1974 (Box 10, Folder 11)
  - U.S. Commission on Civil Rights - Statement on Affirmative Action for Equal Employment Opportunities, Feb. 1973 (Box 10, Folder 12)
  - U.S. Commission on Civil Rights - A Guide to Federal Laws Prohibiting Sex Discrimination Clearinghouse Publication, No 46, 1974 (Box 10, Folder 13)
  - U.S. Congressional Record, issues from, 1974 (Box 10, Folder 14)
  - U.S. Dept. of Health, Education, and Welfare - HEW People Serving People: A Profile of the Department of Health, Education, and Welfare (Box 10, Folder 15)
  - U.S. Dept. of Health, Education, and Welfare - Report of the Women’s Action Program, January 1972 (Box 10, Folder 16)
  - U.S. Dept. of Labor - Laws and Sex Discrimination in Employment, 1970 (Box 10, Folder 17)
  - U.S. Dept. of Labor - Careers for Women in the 70’s, 1973 (Box 10, Folder 18)
  - Women’s Heritage Calendar and Almanac, 1970 (Box 10, Folder 19)
- Publications - Newsletters
  - CCLC Legislative Newsletter, Feb. 1973 - May 1973; Nov. 1973 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - (Coordinating Committee on Legislative Concerns) (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - CCLC Legislative Newsletter, Jan.- May 1974, Vol. II, no. 4 - 13 (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - (Coordinating Committee on Legislative Concerns) (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Do It Now monthly newsletter of NOW, March, August, October 1971 (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Do It Now monthly newsletter of NOW, Jan. - Dec. 1972 (except May and July) (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Do It Now monthly newsletter of NOW, 1973 (all issues except Feb., June, and August) (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Do It Now monthly newsletter of NOW, 1974, Jan. - April; May - July, Sept. - Oct. (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - Do It Now, August 1977, Vol. X, no. 8 (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - Here and Now, February and March 1974 (Box 11, Folder 8)
  - National Ad Hoc Committee for ERA, 1970 issues (Box 11, Folder 9)
  - NOW Newsletter Nashville Chapter, Dec. 1970; newsletter subscription forms (Box 11, Folder 10)
  - NOW Newsletter Nashville Chapter, Jan. - Dec. 1971 (except Feb., Aug.) (Box 11, Folder 11)
  - NOW Newsletter Nashville Chapter, Jan. - July 1972 (Box 11, Folder 12)
  - NOW Newsletter Nashville Chapter, August - December 1972 (Box 11, Folder 13)
  - NOW Newsletter Nashville Chapter, 1973 (Box 11, Folder 14)
  - NOW Newsletter Nashville Chapter, 1974 - Jan., March, April, November, December (Box 11, Folder 15)
  - NOW Notes - newsletter Atlanta Chapter, Feb. 1971 - Nov. 1974 (not all issues) (Box 11, Folder 16)
  - NOWLETTER - newsletter Baton Rouge, Louisiana Chapter, May - June 1971, Aug. 1971 - Jan. 1972 (Box 11, Folder 17)
- Publications - Newsletters
  - NOW Newsletter Chattanooga Area Chapter, April 1973 - October 1973 (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - NOW Newsletter Chattanooga Area Chapter, Feb., April, May, June, July 1974 (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - NOW Newsletter Cleveland, Ohio Chapter, June/July 1972 (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - NOW Newsletter Houston, Texas Chapter, The Broadside - July, September, 1971 (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - NOW Newsletter Huntsville, Alabama Chapter, Jan. 1971 (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - NOW Newsletter Jacksonville, Florida Chapter, April 1971, August 1971, January 1972 (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - NOW Newsletter Knoxville, Tennessee Chapter, April, May, July, August 1974 (Box 12, Folder 7)
  - Louisville NOW newsletter, September 4, 1974 (Box 12, Folder 7)
  - NOW Newsletter Memphis Tennessee Chapter Now in Memphis, March, April, May, July, August 1971 (Box 12, Folder 8)
  - NOW Newsletter Memphis, Tennessee Chapter Now in Memphis, March, April, May, June, August, September, October, November, December 1973 (Box 12, Folder 9)
  - NOW Newsletter Memphis, Tennessee Chapter Now in Memphis, Jan., Feb., March, May, June, July, Aug., November, December 1974 (Box 12, Folder 10)
  - NOW Newsletter Mississippi, 1973, 1974 (Box 12, Folder 11)
  - NOW Newsletter Montgomery County, Maryland, Jan. 1972, Vol.1, no. 1 (Box 12, Folder 12)
  - NOW Newsletter Central New Jersey Chapter, March - September, Nov. 1970 (Box 12, Folder 13)
  - NOW Newsletter Central New Jersey Chapter, March, April, July, August 1971 (Box 12, Folder 14)
  - NOW Newsletter Northern Virginia, June, September, October 1970 (Box 12, Folder 15)
  - NOW Newsletter Northern Virginia, January, February, April, June 1971 (Box 12, Folder 16)
  - NOW Newsletter Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania Know News -, April 27, 1971 (Box 12, Folder 17)
  - NOW Newsletter Texas: Fort Worth - May 1971; San Antonio Say It Now, May 1971, Vol. No. 3, July 1971; Jan. 1972 (Box 12, Folder 18)
  - NOW ACTS - Winter, 1970, Vol.3, no. 1; September 1970, Vol.3, no. 3; Dec. 1970, Vol. 3, no. 4; Summer 1971, Vol.4, no.2; Fall 1971, Vol. 4, no.3; 1972, Vol. 5, no. 1; Feb. 1973, Vol. 6, no.1 (Box 12, Folder 19)
  - The Peabody-Vanderbilt AWP Newsletter (Association for Women in Psychology), August; September 1971; Oct. 1971 (Box 12, Folder 20)
  - The Phyllis Schlafly Report-, Feb. 1972; Nov. 1972; Feb. 1973; March 1973 (Box 12, Folder 21)
- Publications – Newsletters
  - The Southern Poverty Law Center, December 1974 with accompanying materials (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - The Spokeswoman: a monthly information service for all women, July, August, September, October, December 1970, Vol. 1, no. 3 - 7 (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - The Spokeswoman, 1971 - Jan. - May, Vol. 1, no. 8 -11; July - Nov., Vol. 2, no. 1 - 4 (Box 13, Folder 3)
  - The Spokeswoman, 1973 - Jan. - May, Vol. 3, no. 7 - 11 (Box 13, Folder 4)
  - The Vocal Majority: A NOW Newsletter, Washington, D.C., May - Sept. 1971 (Box 13, Folder 5)
  - The Vocal Majority: A NOW Newsletter, Washington, D.C., October 1971 - January 1972 (Box 13, Folder 6)
  - The Woman Activist, 1971 - Jan. - May, Vol. 1, no. 1 - 5; July - Sept.; Oct. -Dec., Vol. 1, no. 7,8, 9,10,11, 12, 13 (Box 13, Folder 7)
  - The Woman Activist, 1972 - Jan., Feb.,March, April, May, June, July, Sept., Oct., Nov., Vol. 2, no. 1 - 4, 5 -7, 9, 10 -11 (Box 13, Folder 8)
  - The Woman Activist, 1973 - Jan., Feb., March, June, July, Sept., Oct., Nov., Vol. 3, no. 1 - 3; 7, 9, 10 (Box 13, Folder 9)
  - The Woman Activist - 1974 - Jan. - May, Vol. 4., no. 1 - 5 (Box 13, Folder 10)
  - The Woman Activist - (Action Bulletin for Women’s Rights) Virginia edition, Nov. 1977, Vol. 7, no. 11 (Box 13, Folder 11)
  - The Woman Activist, 1978 – Jan.-May; July, Vol. 8, no. 1 – 5; 7 (Box 13, Folder 12)
  - The Woman Activist, July 1979, Vol. 9, no. 7 (Box 13, Folder 13)
  - The Woman Activist, July/August 2004, Vol. 34, nos. 7-8 “Personal Account” by Flora Trimmer Crater (Box 13, Folder 14)
  - The Woman Activist - Commemorative Issues, August 1972 Guide to the ’72 Elections; 1973 Campaign Handbook; 1974 Guide to Lobbying; 1975 Status and Strategies for Ratification of the Equal Rights Amendment (Box 13, Folder 15)
  - The Woman Activist – December Gift Issues- Guide for Women Candidates, 1972/73, 1973/74 (Box 13, Folder 16)
  - Women’s Studies Newsletter, Fall 1973, no. 5; with press releases (Box 13, Folder 17)
  - Women Today, Jan. 8, 1973, Vol. III, no. 1; Feb. 19, 1973, Vol. III, no. 4 (Box 13, Folder 18)
  - Womongatherings, Spring, 1998, Vol. 3; Fall 1999, Vol. 5 (Box 13, Folder 19)
  - Yes, ERA! The League of Women Voters, no.4, August 1974 (Box 13, Folder 20)
  - Zero Population Growth National Reporter – Nashville Chapter, April 20, 1971; May 18, 1971; Sept. 21, 1971; Jan. 10, 1972; May 10, 1972, Oct. 10, 1973 (Box 13, Folder 21)
  - Zero Population Growth National Reporter, July/August 1971, Vol.3, no. 8; September 1971, vol. 3, no. 9 (Box 13, Folder 22)
  - Zero Population Growth National Reporter –, October 1971, Vol.3, no. 10; Nov./Dec. 1971, Vol. 3, no. 11 (Box 13, Folder 23)
  - Zero Population Growth National Reporter –, March 1972, Vol.4, no. 3 (Box 13, Folder 24)
  - Zero Population Growth National Reporter, April 1972, Vol.4, no. 4; May 1972, vol. 4, no. 5 (Box 13, Folder 25)
- Publications – Newspapers, journals, magazines
  - Civil Rights Digest, Spring 1974, Vol. 6, no. 3 “Sexism and Racism: Feminist Perspectives” (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - The Great Speckled Bird, March 21, 1971, Vol. 4, no. 12 (Box 14, Folder 2)
  - Life, March 17, 1972 “Dropout Wife” (Box 14, Folder 3)
  - Manhattan Tribune, May 2, 1970 (Box 14, Folder 4)
  - The Militant, March 26, 1971 (Box 14, Folder 5)
  - National NOW Times, Dec. 1977, Vol. X, no. 12 (Official Journal of NOW) (Box 14, Folder 6)
  - National NOW Times, April 1979, Vol. XII, no. 4 (Box 14, Folder 7)
  - National Reporter, June 1972, Vol. 4, no.6 (Box 14, Folder 8)
  - New Directions for Women in New Jersey, Fall 1972; Winter 1973 (Box 14, Folder 9)
  - The New Revolutionary (a Journal for Change with Meaning) - “ Introduction” and “Revolution and the Human Element” (Box 14, Folder 10)
  - New Woman, Nov. - Dec. 1973; Nov.-Dec. 1974 (Box 14, Folder 11)
  - New Woman, Nov. - Dec. 1975; August 1977 (Box 14, Folder 12)
  - The New York Times, August 26, 1981 “Equality Act for Males Passsed by Senate 60 - 39 (Box 14, Folder 13)
  - Off Our Backs: A Women’s Liberation Newspaper, Vol. 1, no. 18 Feb. 26, 1971; Vol. 1, no. 19, March 25, 1971 (Box 14, Folder 14)
  - Off Our Backs: A Women’s Liberation Newspaper, Vol.1 no. 20, April 15, 1971; Vol.1, no. 21, May 6, 1971 (Box 14, Folder 15)
  - Off Our Backs: A Women’s Liberation Newspaper, Vol. IV, no. 7, June 1974 (Box 14, Folder 16)
  - Off Our Backs: A Women’s Liberation Newspaper, Vol. IV, no. 9, Aug. – Sept. 1974, Washington, D.C. (Box 14, Folder 17)
  - Pandora: Washington Women’s News Journal, June 1974 (Box 14, Folder 18)
  - The Second Wave: a Magazine of the New Feminism, Vol. 1, no. 3 – 4 (Box 14, Folder 19)
  - Tennessean - articles on women’s issues (Box 14, Folder 20)
  - Tennessean - articles on women’s issues (Box 14, Folder 21)
  - Tennessean - articles on women’s issues (Box 14, Folder 22)
  - Tennessean - articles on women’s issues (Box 14, Folder 23)
  - Tennessean - articles on women’s issues (Box 14, Folder 24)
  - Tennessean - articles on women’s issues (Box 14, Folder 25)
  - Tennessean - articles on women’s issues (Box 14, Folder 26)
- Publications – Newspapers, journals, and magazines
  - Up from Under: By, for, and about Women, Jan./Feb. 1971 (Box 15, Folder 1)
  - U.S.A. Today, August 22, 1991 (Box 15, Folder 2)
  - USA Today, August 23 - 25, 1991 (Box 15, Folder 3)
  - Vanderbilt Hustler, May 4, 1971, Vol. 82, no. 55; March 17, 1972, Vol. 83, no.46; March 21, 1972, Vol. 83, no. 47; April 14, 1972, Vol. 83, no. 51 (Box 15, Folder 4)
  - Vanderbilt Worker (Box 15, Folder 5)
  - The Wall Street Journal - Articles about women’s movement (Box 15, Folder 6)
  - Women: A Journal of Liberation, Vol. 1, no. 3, Spring 1970; Vol. 2, no. 4 (Box 15, Folder 7)
  - Women’s Free Express, April 1974, Vol.1, no. 2; subscription forms (Box 15, Folder 8)
  - Other newspapers – articles on women’s issues (Box 15, Folder 9)
  - Other newspapers – articles on women’s issues (Box 15, Folder 10)
- Memorabilia
  - Buttons, key rings, and badges from the Women’s movement of the early 1970’s